[Waco] Daughters of the American Revolution: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley records, Inclusive: 1956-2002, undated, Bulk: 1977-2002
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
[Waco] Daughters of the American Revolution: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley records
Inclusive: 1956-2002, undated, Bulk: 1977-2002
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3481
Daughters of the American Revolution: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter, 1976 -
6 document boxes and 2 oversized boxes.
The [Waco] Daughters of the American Revolution: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley records contain materials concerning the organization’s activities in the McLennan County area. These include minutes, scrapbooks, video tapes, yearbooks, programs, clippings, handbooks, and directories.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
The 1890s were a time of heightened patriotism, with many all-male fraternities celebrating an
individual’s ancestors who had fought in the American Revolution. Women were often excluded from this opportunity to celebrate one’s lineage and patriotism. On 1890 October 11, a group of women banded together in Washington, D.C. to counter such exclusion. They formed the National Society, Daughters of the American Revolution (NSDAR). The NSDAR had a three-fold mission of educating the public, historic preservation, and open displays of patriotism. Since its inception, the NSDAR has welcomed over 800,000 members into its ranks.
The popularity of the NSDAR quickly spread across the nation. On 1901 December 5, Mrs. Josie Downs Marshall and fourteen other charter members from McLennan County founded the Henry Downs Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution. Henry Downs was famous for having signed the Mecklenburg Declaration (1775). This declaration has stirred heated controversy in scholarly circles. Its signers from Charlotte, North Carolina, claimed that it was the first declaration of independence crafted in the original thirteen
colonies.
Officers in the Henry Downs Chapter were quite particular concerning those whom they granted membership. Applicants had to be women of eighteen years of age or older who could trace their lineage to a Revolutionary War ancestor. In addition to these genealogical requirements, potential inductees had to exhibit strong moral character as well. The group, in addition to focusing on the three-fold mission of the national organization, was very involved within the local community.
For much of the twentieth century, the Henry Downs Chapter enjoyed relative success and growth. In 1976, as part of a bicentennial project conducted by the chapter, Sara Evans and Urena Johnson sought to create a new chapter of the DAR. One of the primary reasons for this course of action was the difficulty young mothers had in attending the meetings of the Henry Downs Chapter, which had always been held in the afternoon or evenings. Evans and Johnson were able to recruit the thirty-six members necessary in order to start a new chapter. On 1976 October 15, these
women met in an organizational meeting with the purpose of forging a new group: the Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter.
Elizabeth Gordon Bradley was the name chosen for this particular chapter for two reasons. First of all, the NSDAR encouraged new groups in the 1970s to name their chapters after influential females from the Revolutionary period. It was also fitting because this was the ancestor of Sara Evans.
Elizabeth Gordon, the heroine that this group celebrates, was born in Williamsburg Township, South Carolina, on 1730 May 4. In 1750, she married a landowner named Samuel Bradley. The couple openly supported the break from Great Britain. After Samuel’s death in 1778, Elizabeth continued to aid the cause of the Revolution by making clothes and preparing food for the soldiers as well as conducting a makeshift hospital at her home.
Scope and Content
The chronology of the [Waco] Daughters of the American Revolution: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley records ranges from 1956 to 2002, but the bulk of the materials do not predate the mid-1970s. It was during this time, in 1976, that the Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter broke away from the Henry Downs Chapter of the NSDAR. There is a wide range of materials found within the collection. These include minutes from the chapter's inception to the time that the collection was donated (2002), five scrapbooks filled with photographs and certificates, yearbooks, video tapes, newspaper clippings, handbooks, directories, and other printed materials pertaining to teh creation and running of the Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter.
Arrangement
This collection, prior to processing, was well-maintained and well-organized. Similar materials were already grouped together. However, it had not been processed. Currently the collection is organized into four series: I. Minutes, II. Literary Productions, III. Audio/Visual, and IV. Scrapbooks. The materials in Series I. have been arranged chronologically. The remainder of the collection is organized alphabetically by type of material.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3481. Acquired 2002-05-02
Related Resources
Items in related collections
[Waco] Daughters of the American Revolution: Henry Downs Chapter records, Inclusive: 1897-2006, undated, Bulk: 1960-1990
Related references
“About DAR.” Daughters of the American Revolution. Accessed 2012 May 16.
“Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter NSDAR.” Daughters of the American Revolution. Accessed 2012 May 16.
Johnson, Mrs. Hubert. “Daughters of the American Revolution, Henry Downs Chapter.” The Handbook of Waco and McLennan County, Texas. Ed. Dayton Kelley. Waco: Texian Press, 1972.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Daughters of the American Revolution.
Subjects
United States -- History -- Revolution.
Genres
Brochures.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Directories.; Handbooks and manuals.; Minutes (Records); Scrapbooks.
- Minutes, 1979-2001; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The following series is comprised of folders containing the official minutes of the Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution. These papers reveal information such as the election of officers, special luncheons or events, guest speakers, and the financial contributions of the chapter’s members. The materials are in excellent condition.
  - General: (1 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General: (2 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General: (3 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General: (4 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General: (5 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General: (6 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General: (7 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General: (8 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General: (9 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General: (10 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General: (11 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General: (12 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General: (13 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - General: (14 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - General: (15 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - General: (16 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - General: (17 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - General: (18 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - General: (19 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - General: (20 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - General: (21 of 21), 1979-1994 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - General: (1 of 4), 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - General: (2 of 4), 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - General: (3 of 4), 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - General: (4 of 4), 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - General: (1 of 3), 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - General: (2 of 3), 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - General: (3 of 3), 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General: (1 of 5), 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - General: (2 of 5), 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - General: (3 of 5), 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General: (4 of 5), 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General: (5 of 5), 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General: (1 of 4), 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - General: (2 of 4), 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General: (3 of 4), 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - General: (4 of 4), 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Literary Productions, 1956-2002; 2
  This series, the largest of the collection, contains printed materials pertaining to the Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter, including brochures, national and local directories, press books full of newspaper clippings, programs, and yearbooks. These materials are in good to excellent condition.
  - Brochures: Daughters of the American Revolution, 1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Directory: DAR Committees, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Directory: DAR Committees, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Directory: DAR Committees, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Directory: National Society, Daughters of the American Revolution, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Directory: NSDAR, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Directory: NSDAR, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Guides: Membership, 1963, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Guides: Chapter Treasurers, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Handbook: DAR Handbook and National Bylaws, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Handbook: DAR Handbook and National Bylaws, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Handbook: DAR Handbook and National Bylaws, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Handbook: DAR Handbook and National Bylaws, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Handbook: Junior American Citizens, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Manual: “A Public Relations Guideline for Chapters”, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Manual: “DAR Parliamentary Procedure Guide for Chapters”, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Manual: “The ABCs of Public Relations”, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Pamphlet: DAR Schools, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Pamphlet: National Archives, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Press Book: Clippings: (1 of 2), 1993 February-1994 February (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Press Book: Clippings: (2 of 2), 1993 February-1994 February (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Press Book: Clippings: (1 of 2), 1994 March-1995 February (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Press Book: Clippings: (2 of 2), 1994 March-1995 February (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Press Book: Clippings: (1 of 3), 1995 March-1996 February (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Press Book: Clippings: (2 of 3), 1995 March-1996 February (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Press Book: Clippings: (3 of 3), 1995 March-1996 February (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Press Book: Clippings: (1 of 4), 1996 March-1997 February (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Press Book: Clippings: (2 of 4), 1996 March-1997 February (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Press Book: Clippings: (3 of 4), 1996 March-1997 February (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Press Book: Clippings: (4 of 4), 1996 March-1997 February (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Press Book: Clippings: (1 of 3), 1997 March-1998 February (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Press Book: Clippings: (2 of 3), 1997 March-1998 February (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Press Book: Clippings: (3 of 3), 1997 March-1998 February (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Printed Materials: Acts of Incorporation, 1982, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Printed Materials: Application Papers, 1975, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Printed Materials: Organization and Traditions, 1956-1988 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Program: 101st Continental Congress: NSDAR, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Program: 102nd Annual State Conference, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Program: 108th Continental Congress: NSDAR, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Resolutions: NSDAR, 1996, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Registration Book: Meetings, 1986-1990 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Registration Book: Meetings, 1990-2001 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Yearbook: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter, 1976-1977, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Yearbook: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter, 1978-1979, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Yearbook: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter, 1981-1982, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Yearbook: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter, 1983-1984, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Yearbook: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter, 1985-1986, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Yearbook: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter, 1987-1988, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Yearbook: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter, 1989-1990, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Yearbook: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter, 1991-1992, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Yearbook: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter, 1993-1994, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Yearbook: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter, 1995-1996, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Yearbook: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter, 1997-1998, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Yearbook: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter, 1999-2000, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Yearbook: Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter, 2001-2002 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Audio/Visual, 1995; 3
  The following series contains two video tapes created by the Daughters of the American Revolution. The subject matter appears in the titles. The series is in good condition.
  - Video Tape: Historical Contest: “Colonial Music”, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Video Tape: Texas Society Daughters of the American Revolution Centennial, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Scrapbooks, 1976-1998; 4
  This series is comprised of five scrapbooks prepared by the Elizabeth Gordon Bradley Chapter. These scrapbooks are in good to excellent condition.
  - Scrapbook One, 1976-1980 (Box 7 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook Two, 1994-1996 (Box 7 OVZ, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook Three, 1994-1995 (Box 8 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook Four, 1996-1998 (Box 8 OVZ, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook Five: Pages 1-5, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook Five: Pages 6-9, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook Five: Page 10, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook Five: Pages 11-17, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook Five: Pages 18-23, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Scrapbook Five: Pages 24-27, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook Five: Pages 28-36, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook Five: Pages 37, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook Five: Pages 38-44, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook Five: Pages 45-52, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Scrapbook Five: Pages 53-62, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook Five: Pages 63-66, loose, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 15)